Guide to the Spain Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Original accession
  - Part I, 1400-1768
    - Title: "Historia de lo que pasó con el padre fray Froilán Díaz." Place: Madrid? Description: During his life, King Charles II suffered constant illnesses. In 1697, the King got very sick, and rumors that he had been bewitched starting circulating in the Spanish court. This copy is an account of the magical and religious practices used by the confessor of Charles II, Dominican Froilán Díaz, to cure the king, and the inquisitorial process against the Dominican for practicing sorcery., [ca.1704] (Box 7, Folder 105, Reel 4U)
    - Author: Salazar, Luis de. Title: "Memorial que formó ... Por el duque de Medina Coeli, don Luis de la Cerda, y se dio por éste al rey nuestro señor." Description: Copy of a memorial, addressed to King Philip V, on the rents and privileges of the dukes of Medina Coeli., [ca.1706] (Box 7, Folder 106, Reel 4U)
    - Title: Consult. Place: Madrid. Description: Copy of a consult by the Royal Council of Castile, to King Philip V, on the authority of that Council to expel members of religious orders from Spain and confiscate their properties., 1708 September 22 (Box 7, Folder 107, Reel 4U)
    - Author: Salazar, Luis de. Title: "Satisfacción a una consulta del Consejo de Castilla, formada ... A instancia de un ministro de el gavinete." Place: Madrid? Description: Extensive legal writ by Luis de Salazar on the authority of the Council of Castile to expel ecclesiastics from Spain and confiscate their properties., 1708 (Box 7, Folder 108, Reel 5U)
    - Title: "Abcdario índice de las materias que se contienen en los dos tomos de instrucciones y cartas acordadas que se an expedido por el Consejo de la Santa General Inquisición para el mejor govierno de los tribunales del Santo Oficio, según y conforme se guardan y registran en el Consejo hasta el presente año de 1687." Place: Madrid. Description: Book containing an index/summary of the ordinances and agreements (cartas acordadas) issued by the Council of the Supreme and General Inquisition of Madrid concerning the administration of the provincial tribunals, duties and privileges of the personnel, publication of edicts, and rents. The ordinances and agreements are arranged by subject in alphabetical order. This copy was made at the request of a Spanish American tribunal, most probably the tribunal of Lima., 1709 July 23 (Box 7, Folder 109, Reel 5U)
    - Author: Cardinal Portocarrero. Title: "Papel en que se hace presente a su magestad ...los prejuicios y graves inconvenientes que resultarían de las providencias dadas para extinguir en el todo el comercio con la corte de Roma." Place: Madrid. Description: Copy of a memorial, addressed to Philip V, evaluating the consequences of suspending commercial and diplomatic relations between Spain and the papacy., 1709 July 31 (Box 7, Folder 110, Reel 5U)
    - Title: "Consulta del Consejo a su magestad." Place: Madrid. Description: Copy of a consult by the council, to King Philip V, on the sanctions to be applied to deserters in war., 1711 February 16 (Box 7, Folder 111, Reel 5U)
    - Title: "Copia de carta que escribió al rey... Luis Primero el rey... Don Phelipe Quinto, su padre." Place: San Ildefonso. Description: Printed copy of a letter by King Philip V, to his son Luis, in which Philip renounces succession to the Spanish crown in favor of his son., 1724 January 14 (Box 7, Folder 112, Reel 5U)
    - Title: Letter by the Council of Castile. Place: Madrid. Description: Copy of a letter by the Council of Castile, to King Philip V, expressing its condolences upon the death of Luis I., 1724 September 7 (Box 7, Folder 113, Reel 5U)
    - Author: Guerra y Sandoval, Juan Alfonso de. Title: "Despacho y blasón de armas." Place: Madrid. Description: Book containing the family genealogy of Juan Bautista de Peñarredonda Belaz Paraya y la Quintana. Contains six water colors on vellum, including four coats of arms. Genealogy accounts were usually compiled to obtain the title of noble., 1724 (Box 8, Folder 114, Reel 5U)
    - Title: History of the reign of King Philip V of Spain. Description: Partial copy of a history of the reign of King Philip V of Spain between 1712 and 1725. Describes events such as the end of the war of the Spanish Succession, the Treaty of Utrecht, the war of the Triple Alliance against Spain, the conflict between the Inquisition and Melchor Rafael de Macanaz, the brief reign of Luis I, and the assumption of Philip V to the Spanish throne after Luis I's death., [ca.1725]
      - Sections 1-11 (Box 8, Folder 115, Reel 5U)
      - Sections 12-25 (Box 8, Folder 116, Reel 5U)
      - Sections 26-34 (Box 8, Folder 117, Reel 6U)
      - Sections 35-44 (Box 8, Folder 118, Reel 6U)
    - Title: Report to the king. Place: Madrid. Description: Copy of an extensive report, addressed to King Philip V, analyzing requests made by the French ambassador to Spain., [ca.1730]
      - Pages 41-134 (Box 8, Folder 119, Reel 6U)
      - pages 135-250 (Box 8, Folder 120, Reel 6U)
    - Author: Marquis of Castelar. Title: "Declaración dada en 28 de henero, en nombre del rey de España, a los ministros de Ynglaterra, de Francia y de los Estados Generales de las Provincias Unidas." Place: Paris. Description: Memorial by the marquis of Castelar, plenipotentiary ambassador of King Philip V, addressed to the ministers of England, France and the Netherlands, announcing his withdrawal from the diplomatic negotiations held in Paris., 1731 January 28 (Box 9, Folder 121, Reel 6U)
    - Title: Memorial addressed to the General Inquisitor. Place: Madrid? Description: Copy of a memorial, addressed to the General Inquisitor, concerning the banning of Jesuit Gaspar de Astete's "Doctrina Christiana" by the Inquisition. The tribunal had banned the edition of the "Doctrina," printed in Valladolid by Alonso de el Riego, because it contained several doctrinal misinterpretations. The author of this memorial asked the Tribunal to allow the circulation of those editions printed prior to the Valladolid edition., [ca.1736] (Box 9, Folder 122, Reel 6U)
    - Title: Royal decree by the king. Place: El Pardo. Description: Copy of a royal decree by King Philip V nominating his son, Prince Philip, as general admiral of the Spanish naval forces., 1737 March 14 (Box 9, Folder 123, Reel 6U)
    - Title: Documents on the Society of Jesus. Description: Three documents, two printed and one handwritten, related to the controversy between the city of Vitoria and the Society of Jesus over the plan for establishing an institution (college, asylum or residence) by the Jesuits in that city., 1737-1745 (Box 9, Folder 124, Reel 6U)
    - Title: "Dictamen político." Place: Madrid. Description: Copy of a memorial by Joseph Laysequilla, the marquis of la Regalía, Joseph de la Quintana and Joseph de Carvajal, addressed to King Philip V, concerning the sanctions against foreigners who practiced illegal commerce in Spanish America., 1739 January 25 (Box 9, Folder 125, Reel 6U)
    - Title: Memorial to King Philip V. Place: Madrid. Description: Copy of a memorial by the Council, addressed to King Philip V, establishing the policy to be followed by the Casa de Contratación of Seville with foreigners expelled from Spanish America for practicing illegal commerce in that region., 1739 April 18 (Box 9, Folder 126, Reel 6U)
    - Title: Letter to José del Campillo y Cosio. Place: Madrid. Description: Letter by Diego de Bordick? To José del Campillo y Cosio, minister of the hacienda, in which Bordick? Presented a political plan for commercial development in the Spanish dominions., 1741 March 29 (Box 9, Folder 127, Reel 7U)
    - Author: Campillo y Cosio, José del. Title: "España despierta. Críticas e ynstructibas reflexsiones correspondientes a varios e importantísimos asuntos para la mejor organización y régimen de la monarquía española." Place: Madrid? Description: Copy of a plan by José del Campillo y Cosio for the reform of the government, administration, agriculture, commerce, legislation and society in Spain., 1742 February 27 (Box 9, Folder 128, Reel 7U)
    - Title: Memorials by the Spanish Catholic church. Places: Madrid, Zaragoza. Description: Copies of documents related to the collection of ecclesiastical contributions for the Spanish crown: "Memorial de la Santa Iglesia de Toledo, primada de España, al Nuncio de Su Santidad, sobre la contribución del ocho por ciento que se mandó exigir de los eclesiásticos" (n.d.); "Memorial de la Santa Iglesia de Toledo al rey" (n.d.); "Copia de carta de la Santa Iglesia de Toledo... En respuesta de otra del ... Señor arzobispo de Edesa, nuncio de su santidad, sobre la contribución del ocho por ciento" (n.d.); "Carta escripta al ... Señor nuncio de España por el ... Cavildo metropolitano de Zaragoza" (22 Feb 1742); "Respuesta del ... Nuncio a la antecedente" (Madrid, 3 Mar 1742); and "Carta del... Cavildo al ... Nuncio de España respondiendo a la antezedente" (Zaragoza, 13 Mar 1742). (Box 9, Folder 129, Reel 7U)
    - Author: Campillo y Cosio, José del. Place: Madrid. Title: "Nuevo sistema de gobierno económico para la América. Con los males y daños que le causa el que hoy tiene de los que participa copiosísamente España. Y remedios universales para que la primera tenga considerables ventajas y la segunda mayores intereses. Primera parte." Place: Madrid. Description: Among the numerous texts written by Spanish authors to provide useful guides for economic and political reforms in colonial Spanish America, the "Nuevo sistema" by Campillo was perhaps the most significant and influential. Some historians have considered Campillo's text a source which inspired the Bourbon reforms. The text is handwritten and is probably a copy made at the time of the original. It is organized in ten chapters, and examines the role of colonial authorities as promoters of reforms, the development of commerce and agriculture, and control over local production and manufacture by the Spanish crown., 1743 February 8 (Box 9, Folder 130, Reel 7U)
    - Title: Documents on the Inquisition of Llerena. Place: Buen Retiro, Madrid. Description: Copies of two documents related to the controversy between the Inquisition and the local authorities of Llerena: a consult by Alonso de Muñiz, bishop of Teruel and general inquisitor, to the Council of Castile, on the legal status of the officers (familiares) of the Inquisition; and a response by the Council of Castile., 1747 (Box 9, Folder 131, Reel 7U)
    - Author: Casaus, Juan. Title: "Reflexiones de... Sobre los medios que se pueden tomar para el fomento de fábricas de todas especies y del comercio interno y externo de España." Description: Copy of plan by Juan Casaus for promoting manufacture and commerce in Spain., 1748 (Box 9, Folder 132, Reel 7U)
    - Author: Pavía, Francisco. Title: "Proyecto... Para fomento del comercio, agricultura y fábricas de estos reinos." Description: Copy of a plan by Francisco Pavía for developing commerce, agriculture and manufacturing in Spain, and colonizing its territory., 1749 (Box 9, Folder 133, Reel 7U)
    - Title: Documents on tax reform. Place: Madrid. Description: Two documents on the plan to reform taxes: a printed "Real decreto de su magestad para que, con arreglo a la instrucción, formularios y planes que le acompañan, se averiguen los efectos en que pueden fundarse una sola contribución, para el mayor alivio de sus vasallos, en lugar de las que componen las rentas provinciales" (Buen Retiro, 10 October 1749); and a compilation entitled "órdenes y resoluciones de la Real Junta de la única contribución, desde diez y ocho de abril de 1750." The compilation includes an index., 1749-1754 (Box 10, Folder 134, Reel 7U)
    - Title: "Ordenanzas que en lo particular de la marina, navíos y buques... Ha formado la real compañía de comercio establecida en Barcelona." Description: Original text of the ordinances issued by the Real Compañía de Comercio, founded in Barcelona, to be followed by the crews of its ships involved in commerce with the islands of Santo Domingo, Puerto Rico and Margarita, and Honduras., 1756 May 4 (Box 10, Folder 135, Reel 8U)
    - Author: Gandara, Miguel Antonio de la. Title: Report. Place: Madrid. Description: Copy of a report by Miguel Antonio de la Gandara, to the marquis of Campo de Villar, on a legal controversy with the bishop of Avila., 1760 March 31 (Box 10, Folder 136, Reel 8U)
    - Title: Documents related to the banning of the "Exposición de la doctrina christiana." Place: Madrid. Description: Copy of documents related to the controversy between the Spanish crown and the Inquisition over the banning of the catechism entitled "Exposición de la doctrina christiana sobre las principales verdades de la religión cathólica.", 1761 (Box 10, Folder 137, Reel 8U)
    - Title: "Aniceto a Cándido." Description: Partial draft of a discourse, with annotations probably by the author, on a plan to reform the society and economy of Spain., [ca.1762] (Box 10, Folder 138, Reel 8U)
    - Title: "Aniceto a Cándido." Description: Copy of text previously described., [ca.1762]
      - Sections 1-12 (Box 11, Folder 139, Reel 8U)
      - Sections 13-29 (Box 11, Folder 140, Reel 8U)
    - Author: Valle Salazar, Luis del. Title: Legal writ. Description: Draft of a legal writ by Luis Valle Salazar on the admission into Spain of the Jesuits expelled from France., [ca.1762] (Box 11, Folder 141, Reel 8U)
    - Title: Consult. Place: Madrid. Description: Copy of a consult by the Council of Castile, to King Charles III, on the election of the provincial of the Trinitarian order in Andalusia., 1765 January 9 (Box 11, Folder 142, Reel 8U)
    - Title: Memorial. Place: Madrid? Description: Draft and final version of an extensive memorial, addressed to King Charles III, on the payment of tithes by the Society of Jesus in Spanish America. Contains information on the three century controversy between the Society of Jesus and prelates and secular clergy over the payment of tithes., [ca.1765] (Box 12, Folder 143 - 144, Reel 8U)
    - Title: Documents on the "labor de la nueva moneda." Place: Madrid. Description: Collection of consults and reports related to the minting of the new "vellón" coin., 1766-1773 (Box 12, Folder 145 - 148, Reel 9U)
    - Title: Correspondence between the pope, the Austrian empress and the king of Spain. Places: Rome, Viena, San Ildefonso. Description: Copies of three letter between the pope; Maria Theresa, empress of Austria; and Charles III, king of Spain; related to the papal censorship of the duke of Parma., 1768 (Box 12, Folder 149, Reel 9U)
  - Part II, 1505-1891
    Part II is 1.5 linear feet; the majority is comprised of originals and copies of materials from Spain. The collection includes state documents such as decrees, ordinances, wills and reports; ecclesiastical texts; church documents; correspondence; accounts of events; political writings; and literary texts. They cover a broad period of Spanish history, from the beginning of the sixteenth until the end of the nineteenth century. The majority of documents date to the period of the monarchs of the Bourbon dynasty: Philip V (1700-1746), Ferdinand VI (1746-1759), Charles III (1759-1788), and Charles IV (1788-1808).
    Because King Charles II named a member of France's House of Bourbon, Philip, the duke of Anjou and a grandson of Louis XIV, as his successor, the French became deeply involved in Spanish affairs. This is best documented by a report on the conduct of the princess of Ursino in Spain, who came to dominate the royal court in the early years of the reign of Philip V (1700-1746).
    The "Bourbon Reforms" were aimed at encouraging the social and economic development of Spain and her colonies. Most useful for the study of the reforms is a report by Francisco Cabarrus dealing with the need to grant the Banco de San Carlos a monopoly on silver extraction. There are materials by Manuel José de Ayala, a distinguished jurist, who sought to modernize and publish Spanish laws governing the Indies. They include an index to numerous volumes of Ayala's materials which show what he considered important to his legal thinking. Finally, there is a report urging the establishment of a new royal trading company for the Indies so that Spain, rather than other foreign powers, would profit from the Iberian empire.
    The reign of Charles III (1759-1788) witnessed the beginning of the "Age of Revolution" when England's North American colonies fought for their independence. A report (1783) examining the threat that the newly independent United States posed to Spain's colonies sheds light on the impact of this event on Spain.
    The reign of Charles IV (1788-1808) witnessed the French Revolution and its subsequent events, which culminated in the invasion of Spain by the forces of Napoleon in 1808. Several manuscripts capture the turbulence of the era, including a letter from the Spanish ambassador in Paris describing the state of Franco-Spanish relations; an appeal by Gaspar de Jovellanos, a dominant figure of the Spanish enlightenment, for justice after his imprisonment on Majorca; a report dealing with the Spanish defeat at the Battle of Trafalgar; and a denunciation of the French invasion by Pascual Solono y Noboa.
    The Napoleonic invasion of Iberia led to the beginnings of independence movements in Spain's Latin American colonies. Spain's struggle to maintain its empire is documented in a series of reports discussing foreign trade in the Americas and seeking the re-establishment of the system of "comercio libre," as it had functioned prior to the wars; plans for the reconquest of the colonies detailing the means by which Spain could achieve this feat; and a diplomatic note from the American minister to Spain urging the king to accept the loss of the American colonies. In addition, a series of orders from the king of Spain addressed to the count of Cartagena detail the restoration of the "liberal" order in 1820.
    - Title: Royal decree. Description: Decree issued by Queen Juana concerning the property rights of the duke of [Infantado?] in the Spanish cities of Guadarama and Colmenar Viejo., 1505 February 4 (Box 13, Folder 1, Reel 10U)
    - Title: Miscellaneous index. Place: Madrid? Description: Index to a volume of miscellaneous documents., 1555-1632 (Box 13, Folder 2, Reel 10U)
    - Title: Royal grant. Description: Royal grant by King Philip II to Pedro Ribero, his heirs and successors., 1574 December 14 (Box 13, Folder 3, Reel 10U)
    - Title: Royal instructions. Place: Vienna. Description: Series of instructions issued by King [Charles I?] of Spain to the heads of tribunals and civil departments concerning the conduct of public business., [15--?] (Box 13, Folder 4, Reel 10U)
    - Author: Brandon, Lorenco. Title: Report on money. Description: Handwritten copy of a report dealing with the value of silver and other issues related to currency. "British Museum, Papeles Varios 1322 l. 7 MS 1(3)" appears on the first page., 1623 August 18 (Box 13, Folder 5, Reel 10U)
    - Title: Report on the seizure of Evora. Description: Report about the seizure of Evora, Portugal, by Spanish troops. The document includes a copy of a letter written by the Ottoman sultan to the king of Spain, and a listing of other news and events., 1663-1664 (Box 13, Folder 6, Reel 10U)
    - Title: "Relación del memorial que el Señor Duque de Medina presentó a su magestad...." Place: Madrid. Description: Request by the duke of Medina Celi that he be allowed to resign as prime minister. King Charles II grants the request., 1685 April 18 (Box 13, Folder 7, Reel 10U)
    - Title: Archival guide. Description: Handwritten guide to an unidentified record group in a [Spanish?] archive. A brief summary of each document is provided. These documents mainly deal with currency issues and the silver trade. In Spanish with some English passages. "Papeles Varios 1322, L. 7, 1-40" appears on the first page of the text., 1686 (Box 13, Folder 8, Reel 10U)
    - Title: Letter from the king of Spain to the bishop of Pamplona. Place: Madrid. Description: Letter dealing with the resolution of a conflict over ecclesiastical immunity in the Kingdom of Navarre., 1695 March 24 (Box 13, Folder 9, Reel 10U)
    - Title: Letter by the Emperor Leopold to Pope Innocent XII. Place: Vienna. Description: Letter concerning the way in which the Spanish Inquisition was proceeding against banned texts., 1696 January 20 (Box 13, Folder 10, Reel 10U)
    - Title: Last will and testament of the Queen Mother. Place: Madrid. Description: Copy of the last will and testament of Mariana de Austria, wife of Philip IV, and mother of Charles II of Spain., 1696 May 10 (Box 13, Folder 11, Reel 10U)
    - Title: "Relación de achaques y muerte de su magestad la reyna madre de nuestro monarcha." Place: Madrid? Description: Report which briefly describes the illness suffered by the Spanish queen mother. Also detailed are the funeral honors accorded her., 1696 (Box 13, Folder 12, Reel 10U)
    - Title: "Defensa de la Valtelina en su procedimientos contra los Grisones." Description: Brief document stating offenses committed against the Catholic faith, and within the temporal realm, by the Grisones, a confederated people living in northern Italy, who controlled the Valley of Valtelina., [16--?] (Box 13, Folder 13, Reel 10U)
    - Title: Letter by Miguel Calderon de la Barca to the duchess of Medina Sedonia. Description: Correspondence about the loss of letters concerning an encomienda in Campeche. Copies of the original letters are also included., 1712 May 30 (Box 13, Folder 14, Reel 10U)
    - Title: "Papeles varios." Description: Bound handwritten volume which contains speeches, discourses, poetry, proclamations, military documents, and other writings by, or copied by, [François Antoine Boissy 'Anglas?], 1744-1813 (Box 13, Folder 15, Reel 10U)
    - Title: Valuation. Place: New Orleans. Description: Handwritten English language copy of a valuation of all buildings owned by the king, in New Orleans, made by public officials and representatives from the building trades., 1769, 1819 (Box 13, Folder 16, Reel 10U)
    - Title: Confirmation of baptism. Description: Document confirming that on January 4, 1756, Manuel Silvestre de Conde was baptized in the Catholic faith., 1774 April 15 (Box 13, Folder 17, Reel 10U)
    - Title: Ship Registries. Place: Cádiz. Description: Printed registries of the "fragata" La Aguila and the "navio" La Concepción., 1776 January 11-18 (Box 13, Folder 18, Reel 10U)
    - Title: Diary. Place: Rome? Description: The diary, in Spanish, of an unidentified individual, probably written in Rome. The text records notable events of the time in Spain, Italy, Germany, Russia, Turkey, and other locations., 1782 January - 1783 February (Box 13, Folder 19, Reel 10U)
    - Author: Cabarrus, Francisco. Title: Report concerning silver extraction. Description: Report concerning the need to grant the recently established Banco de San Carlos (national bank) a monopoly on silver extraction (extracción)., 1783 September 5 (Box 13, Folder 20, Reel 10U)
    - Title: "Dictamen reservado que el Conde de Aranda dió al rey sobre la independencia de las colonias ingleses, después de haber firmado el tratado de paz ajustado en Paris en el año de 1783." Description: Handwritten report to the king of Spain analyzing the threat that the newly independent United States posed to the Spanish empire. The report proposed creating three new Spanish kingdoms in the New World. (Box 13, Folder 21, Reel 10U)